And welcome to this
presentation of Safespring's
self-service portal.
In this portal, you will be able to
create and set up your own Kubernetes
clusters.
Let's get started.
You go to the portal by going to portal.
safespring. com, where
you have a Sign in button.
And as you can see now, when I press
Sign in, I will be directed to this
page, where I choose Continue
with Safespring Provider.
And right now my user
session is cached, so
this means that I will
be logged in directly.
But if this is the first time you do this,
you might be directed to the IdP
connected to the portal, where your
account resides, and that is
part of the onboarding process.
Let's press Continue with Safespring
Provider, and we will be presented
with this view, where you
have a number of environments.
An environment is a way of
grouping your resources together.
Today, you can have several
clusters in one environment,
but in the future you will also be
able to set up compute infrastructure
projects and S3 storage accounts.
Let's go down to this one.
And you can see here that this
environment is completely empty,
and therefore I can add a cluster.
And here you can also see the
other buttons that will be
available soon.
So I just press Add Cluster,
and I give my cluster a name.
This is the first step in
creating a new Kubernetes cluster.
So I just call it safe-test-01.
Then I press Next.
And now I can choose
which data center I would
like to provision my resources in.
I'm going to pick Stockholm 2 here,
because GPU flavors are also available
there.
I will not use them right
now, but that is one
difference between the two.
Otherwise, it could simply be geographical
or sovereignty reasons why you choose
either of the two.
So I go with Stockholm 2 and press Next.
And now it's time to configure how
many control plane nodes I'm going to
have and which type to use.
More precisely, I choose three
nodes, and I can choose their sizing.
And you can see that there are
different flavor variants here.
You can have four vCPUs per control plane
node, eight gigabytes of RAM,
and 100 gigabytes of storage.
But there are also other variants.
I'm just going to go with
the smallest one here.
So: four vCPUs, eight
gigabytes of RAM, and 100 GB of
storage.
Then it's time to
provision my worker nodes.
And you can see here that I can choose
different numbers of them with this
slider.
I'm just going to choose
three here, and I'm
going to take the smallest one.
You can also see that you
have those GPU flavors here.
And in the future there will also be
something more like a shopping cart
here, where you might have
a use case in which you
would like three worker
nodes of this type and
maybe just two GPU worker nodes.
You might not want to have all
your nodes running with GPU
flavors.
Those are only needed
for certain applications.
But right now I'm just going to pick
the smallest one: eight vCPUs, 16 GB
of RAM, and 100 GB of storage per node.
And then I press Next.
And now you can see a summary screen, where
you can review what you're about to do.
It says which environment I'm in
and which data center I'm going to
provision the resources in.
And you can see the name of the cluster,
safe-test-01; the control plane, which
consists of three nodes of this flavor;
and the worker nodes, which consist
of three nodes of this flavor.
It's also possible to download
this configuration for later
provisioning.
So right now we're just going
to select Create Cluster.
And now it has started.
It says that your request
was submitted successfully,
and you see the same
review information again.
So I can select Return to Environment.
You can see here that I now have
this cluster in the environment, with
this ID.
The ID is automatically generated,
and you're going to see that
it also appears elsewhere in
the naming.
When you set up this cluster,
we also
provision DNS automatically,
with a DNS name.
This is the name that
you point your CNAMEs to
in your DNS, so that you can
publish your own applications
running in the cluster.
And you can see here that
it is still being created.
So it's working, and it takes maybe
a minute or two because of what it is
doing now.
It is setting up the control plane,
setting up and provisioning the worker
nodes, and also doing the
DNS provisioning that I
talked about.
There are several other things that
we need to do in order to get the
environment up and running.
I can also tell you that it is
based on Talos Linux from the
ground up, which is an
ephemeral OS, only API-based.
There is no CLI connection
to the Talos nodes,
and this makes it rather easy to
foresee the consequences when we perform
upgrades and things like that.
And that is, of course, part of the
solution: we will manage the control
plane.
That means that when there is an
upgrade to the Kubernetes version, or
something similar, we will be
able to perform those upgrades.
Some upgrades can be a little larger
and can affect the applications
running in the cluster.
In that case,
the upgrade will be done in collaboration
between the team at Safespring
and your application team, so that
they can coordinate and make sure that
all your YAML files and similar resources
work with the newer
version of the environment.
Now it is active, as you can see.
So now we can click the name
here and view our cluster.
We have an overview here.
We have the region—Stockholm 2,
as we said before—which is the
data center where it is running.
You can see the Kubernetes version,
the Talos version, and the underlying
operating system.
And you can also see the network.
Here you have the API endpoint.
This is the name that you can use to
run your kubectl commands against the
cluster.
You can also see the IP address
that has been provisioned.
It also comes with an
automatically configured ingress.
I spoke about that before: we have
this automatically generated DNS
record, which looks pretty long.
But you only need to copy this once
and add it as a CNAME for your own
domain.
Then you can set up your
own ingress resources
in the cluster to match the name you have
configured, with the CNAME
pointing to this address.
In that case, you will be able
to serve applications from
the cluster.
And just one more thing here:
you can see a little button for
scaling the number of worker
nodes.
We can actually scale up.
We had three from the beginning,
so now we can perhaps have
four instead.
I can just select Scale Cluster here.
And you can see that this sends
an order to our provisioning
system.
Let's say that it will scale
the cluster to four nodes.
And if we go back to the environment,
we can see that it is creating again.
This operation takes
far less time because it
is just one worker node that needs to be
provisioned, and everything
else is already there.
So we're just going to wait a
little bit for it to finish.
And you can see that
it now has four nodes.
Now it's finished.
The cluster is active again, so we can
go in and look at the overview page.
And we can see that it
now has four nodes here.
So we managed to scale it up.
But now, what do we do with this?
Well, we want to connect to it, of course.
And we have this button up here
called Kubeconfig, which I'm going to
press.
And here you have the full
configuration of the cluster.
So I'm just going to
copy this, and then I'm
going to go to my terminal.
Now I'm in the terminal.
So I'm going to copy the contents from
the portal into my kubeconfig file.
So I'm just going to open the
kubeconfig file and paste it
here.
I can go through this briefly.
First, we have the certificate
authority data and the
keys that are needed in
order to connect to the cluster correctly.
You can also see the
server for the cluster.
This is the API endpoint that
we also saw in the portal.
But one interesting thing is down
here: when we start running commands
against this cluster,
we will need to log in.
And this is the IDM
connected to Stockholm 2.
You can see it here.
That's where I will need an account
in order to connect to the cluster.
In this way, we have two
levels of identity providers.
We have the IdP for the
portal, where you as
an administrator can set up new clusters.
But you also need another level: the
IdPs for the actual data centers where
those clusters are provisioned.
In this way, you as an administrator
can be in command of setting up and
deleting clusters.
But you can give permissions to certain
users who only have an account in
the IdP connected to the data center.
So you have a layered access model.
This makes it easy to
separate responsibilities,
so that technicians working with the
clusters do not have the right to
delete the clusters, for instance.
So I'm just going to save this here.
And then we can do the regular setup.
I'm going to read this file and set
my KUBECONFIG environment variable to
point to it.
So now I have added the information to the
kubeconfig file, as you can see here.
And now I'm going to set my
KUBECONFIG environment variable to
point to it.
So now the KUBECONFIG environment
variable points to my new kubeconfig
file.
Now I can run kubectl
get nodes, for instance.
And as you can see, I now need
to log in to the IdP where my
account is.
So I'm going to do that.
I enter my password here.
Then I have two-factor
authentication enabled,
so I need to use my hardware key.
And as you can see, I
am now authenticated.
If we go back here, we can see that
I actually got a response from the
command.
So now I have an authentication token.
Now I can run kubectl get pods
--namespace kube-system, for
instance.
Here we can see all the
components running in the cluster.
You can see that we're running Cilium for
networking and CoreDNS for DNS
handling in the environment.
We have Cinder CSI.
This is because we're running
our environment on OpenStack,
where Cinder is the volume service.
This is the plugin that handles the
provisioning of PVCs—persistent volume
claims.
And then we have the other, more
standard Kubernetes services that run in
all Kubernetes clusters.
So this was it.
We have created a cluster
and connected to it.
And now, if I am finished
with this cluster, I can also
delete it.
So I can go here.
This is something I can do
as an administrator of the
environment.
I need to enter the name,
because otherwise it
will not let me continue.
So now I can delete the cluster,
and it will be deprovisioned.
I hope you liked this demonstration,
and I hope to see you soon.
Bye.